Wei Chu

Personal Information

U.S. Permanent Resident Email: email.chuwei@gmail.com

Phone: 206-471-4732 Homepage: https://weichu.github.io/

ABOUT ME

I am an R&D team leader and an award-winning researcher with over 15 years of well-balanced academia and industry experience. I am a senior director & researcher of Ant Group now, leading a team of 100+ researchers and engineers to develop cognitive computing services, including computer vision, natural language understanding and knowledge graph platforms. Previously I was the head of PAI 2.0, Alibaba Cloud's distributed machine learning platform. Prior to joining Alibaba, I was the team leader at Microsoft Bing developing personalized search technology. At Yahoo! Labs I worked with colleagues on web-scale user-click stream for content optimization.

I completed three years of postdoc training at the Gatsby Computational Neuroscience Unit, UCL, mentored by Prof. Zoubin Ghahramani in the field of statistical machine learning, and also conducted two years of applied research at CCLS, Columbia University. I received my Ph.D. degree from the National University of Singapore, under the joint guidance of Prof. S. Sathiya Keerthi and Prof. Chong Jin Ong.

My main interest is to develop learning algorithms that transform large-scale machine-readable data into human-comprehensible knowledge that not only has a major impact on human life, but also makes machine intelligence more equitable and trustworthy. I have published extensively in top-tier conferences and journals including AAAI, ACL, CVPR, ICML, JMLR and NIPS, and have been cited over 10,000 times according to Google Scholar.

Work Experience

Senior Director of Engineering, Jul. 2018 – present

Director of Engineering, Jul. 2017 – Jul. 2018

Cognitive Computing, Ant Group, Alibaba Group, Bellevue, USA

Leading an R&D team of 150 researchers and engineers to develop multi-modal learning solutions for computer vision, natural language understanding and knowledge graph.

Director of Engineering, Nov. 2014 – Jul. 2017

Large Scale Learning, Alibaba Cloud, Alibaba Group, Hangzhou, China

An R&D team leader to develop a distributed machine learning platform, and deliver the platform product PAI 2.0 to Alibaba Cloud, including the implementation of hundreds of distributed learning algorithms on clusters and online services of predictive models.

Principal Applied Scientist Lead, Jan. 2014 – Nov. 2014

Senior Applied Researcher, May 2011 – Jan. 2014

Contextual Relevance, Bing, Microsoft, Seattle, USA

A team leader at Microsoft Bing to deliver personalized search service.

Scientist, Jan. 2008 – May 2011

Audience Science, Yahoo! Lab, Sunnyvale, USA

Working with colleagues on web-scale user click streams for content optimization.

Associate Research Scientist, Jan. 2006 – Jan. 2008

Center for Computational Learning Systems, Columbia University, New York, USA

Conducting independent research on pragmatic Bayesian techniques.

Honors and Awards

- Test of Time Award, ACM SIGIR, 2022
- Best Demo Award, ACM CIKM, 2017
- Best Paper Award, ACM WSDM, 2011
- Super Star Team Award, Yahoo!, 2008
- Honorable Mention Team, ACM KDD CUP, 2002

EDUCATION

Post Doctoral, Feb. 2003 – Jan. 2006

Gatsby Computational Neuroscience Unit, University College London (UCL), UK

Advisor: Prof. Zoubin Ghahramani

Ph.D., Jul. 1999 – Jan. 2003

National University of Singapore (NUS), Singapore

Advisor: Prof. Sathiya Keerthi and Prof. Chong Jin Ong

Master of Engineering, Sept. 1995 – Jan. 1998

Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China

Bachelor of Engineering, Sept. 1991 – Jul. 1995

Harbin Engineering University, Harbin, China

Publications

- 1. L. Zhang, X. Yan, J. He, R. Li, and W. Chu (2023) DRGCN: Dynamic evolving initial residual for deep graph convolutional networks, AAAI 2023
- 2. W. Li, C. Zou, M. Wang, F. Xu, J. Zhao, R. Zheng, Y. Cheng, and W. Chu (2023) DC-Former: Diverse and compact transformer for person re-identification, AAAI 2023
- 3. J. Xu, W. Xu, M. Sun, T. Wang and W. Chu (2022) Extracting trigger-sharing events via an event matrix, Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics: EMNLP 2022
- 4. Q. Guo, K. Yao, and W. Chu (2022) Switch-BERT: Learning to model multimodal interactions by switching attention and input, ECCV 2022: 330-346
- 5. T.-T. Liang, X. Chu, Y. Liu, Y. Wang, Z. Tang, W. Chu, J. Chen, and H. Ling (2022) CBNet: A composite backbone network architecture for object detection, IEEE Trans. Image Process 31: 6893-6906
- 6. W. Hong, J. Lao, W. Ren, J. Wang, J. Chen, W. Chu (2022) Training object detectors from scratch: An empirical study in the era of vision transformer, CVPR 2022: 4652-4661
- 7. H. Wang, T.-W. Chang, T. Liu, J. Huang, Z. Chen, C. Yu, R. Li, W. Chu (2022) ESCM2: Entire space counterfactual multi-task model for post-click conversion rate estimation, SIGIR 2022: 363-372
- 8. K. Ji, J. Liu, W. Hong, L. Zhong, J. Wang, J. Chen, W. Chu (2022) CRET: Cross-modal retrieval transformer for efficient text-video retrieval, SIGIR 2022: 949-959
- 9. M. Li, X. Lin, X. Chen, J. Chang, Q. Zhang, F. Wang, T. Wang, Z. Liu, W. Chu, D. Zhao and R. Yan (2022) Keywords and instances: A hierarchical contrastive learning framework unifying hybrid granularities for text generation, ACL 2022: 4432-4441
- 10. F. Yu, K. Huang, M. Wang, Y. Cheng, W. Chu, and C. Li (2022) Width & depth pruning for vision transformers, AAAI 2022: 3143-3151

- 11. H. Huang, Y. Wang, Z. Chen, Y. Zhang, Y. Li, Z. Tang, W. Chu, J. Chen, W. Lin, and K.-K. Ma (2022) CMUA-Watermark: A cross-model universal adversarial watermark for combating deepfakes, AAAI 2022: 989-997
- 12. L. Chao, J. He, T. Wang and W. Chu (2021) PairRE: Knowledge graph embeddings via paired relation vectors, ACL 2021: 4360-4369
- 13. F. Xu, M. Wang, W. Zhang, Y. Cheng and W. Chu (2021) Discrimination-aware mechanism for fine-grained representation learning, CVPR 2021: 813-822
- 14. W. Hong, P. Guo, W. Zhang, J. Chen and W. Chu (2021) LPSNet: A lightweight solution for fast panoptic segmentation, CVPR 2021: 16746-16754
- W. Hong, K. Ji, J. Liu, J. Wang, J. Chen and W. Chu (2021) GilBERT: Generative vision-language pre-training for image-text retrieval, SIGIR 2021: 1379-1388
- 16. C. Jiang, K. Huang, S. He, X. Yang, W. Zhang, X. Zhang, Y. Cheng, L. Yang, Q. Wang, F. Xu, T. Pan and W. Chu (2021) Learning segment similarity and alignment in large-scale content based video retrieval, ACM MM 2021
- 17. K. Chen, W. Xu, X. Cheng, X. Zou, Y. Zhang, L. Song, T. Wang, Y. Qi and W. Chu (2020) Question directed graph attention network for numerical reasoning over text, EMNLP 2020:6759-6768
- L. Chao, J. Chen and W. Chu (2020) Variational connectionist temporal classification, ECCV 2020:460-476
- X. Cheng, W. Xu, K. Chen, T. Wang, S. Jiang, F. Wang, W. Chu and Y. Qi (2020) SpellGCN: Incorporating phonological and visual similarities into language models for Chinese Spelling Check, ACL 2020:871-881
- 20. X. Lin, W. Jian, J. He, T. Wang, and W. Chu (2020) Generating informative conversational response using recurrent knowledge-interaction and knowledge-copy, ACL 2020:41-52
- 21. F. Xu, W. Zhang, Y. Cheng and W. Chu (2020) Metric learning with equidistant and equidistributed triplet-based loss for product image search, WWW 2020:57-65
- 22. S. Wang, B. Zhu, C. Li, M. Wu, J. Zhang, W. Chu, and Y. Qi (2020) Riemannian proximal policy optimization, Computer and Information Science 13(3)
- 23. W. Zhang, Y. Cheng, X. Guo, Q. Guo, J. Wang, Q. Wang, C. Jiang, M. Wang, F. Xu and W. Chu (2020) Automatic car damage assessment system: reading and understanding videos as professional insurance inspectors, AAAI 2020:13646-13647 Demonstration Track
- 24. W. Huang, X. Cheng, K. Chen, T. Wang, W. Chu (2020) Towards fast and accurate neural Chinese word segmentation with multi-criteria learning, COLING 2020:2062-2072
- 25. C. Li, X. Yan, X. Deng, Y. Qi, W. Chu, L. Song, J. Qiao, J. He and J. Xiong (2019) Latent dirichlet allocation for Internet price war, AAAI 2019:639-646
- 26. X. Cheng, W. Xu, T. Wang, W. Chu, W. Huang, K. Chen and J. Hu (2019) Variational semi-supervised aspect-term sentiment analysis via transformer, CoNLL 2019:961-969
- 27. W. Huang, X. Cheng, T. Wang and W. Chu (2019) BERT-based multi-head selection for joint entity-relation extraction, NLPCC (2) 2019:713-723
- 28. W. Sui, Q. Zhang, J. Yang and W. Chu (2018) A novel integrated framework for learning both text detection and recognition, ICPR 2018:2233-2238
- 29. T. Yin, X. Deng, Y. Qi, W. Chu, J. Pan, X. Yan and J. Xiong (2018) Personalized behavior prediction with encoder-to-decoder structure, NAS 2018:1-10
- 30. J. Yu, M. Qiu, J. Jiang, J. Huang, S. Song, W. Chu and H. Chen (2018) Modelling domain relationships for transfer learning on retroeval-based question answering systems in E-commerce, ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM-11):682-690

- 31. M. Qiu, P. Zhao, K. Zhang, X. Shi, X. Wang, J. Huang and W. Chu (2017) A short-term rainfall prediction model using multi-task convolutional neural networks, IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM)
- 32. F. Li et al. (2017) AliMe Assist: an intelligent assistant for creating an innovative E-commerce experience, ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM) Best Demo Award
- 33. M. Qiu, F.-L. Li, S. Wang, X. Gao, Y. Chen, W. Zhao, H. Chen, J. Huang and W. Chu (2017) AliMe Chat: A Sequence to Sequence and Rerank based Chatbot Engine, Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-55 Short Paper)
- 34. J. Yang, Y. Chen, S. Wang, L. Li, C. Meng, M. Qiu, W. Chu (2017) Practical lessons of distributed deep learning, Workshop on Principled Approaches to Deep Learning at ICML
- 35. B. Bi, H. Ma, B. Hsu, **W. Chu**, K. Wang and J. Cho (2015) Learning to recommend related entities to search users, ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM-08):139-148
- 36. J. Yan, W. Chu, R. W. White (2014) Cohort modeling for enhanced personalized search, ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR-37)
- 37. X. Li, C. Guo, **W. Chu**, Y. Wang, J. Shavlik (2014) Deep learning powered in-session contextual ranking using clickthrough data, Workshop on Personalization: Methods and Applications, at Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)
- 38. H. Wang, X. He, M. Chang, Y. Song, R. W. White, **W. Chu** (2013) Personalized ranking model adaptation for web search, ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR-36)
- 39. R. W. White, **W. Chu**, A. Hassan, X. He, Y. Song, H. Wang (2013) Enhancing personalized search by mining and modeling task behavior, International World Wide Web Conference (WWW-22)
- 40. H. Wang, Y. Song, M. Chang, X. He, R. W. White, **W. Chu** (2013) Learning to extract cross-session search tasks, International World Wide Web Conference (WWW-22):1353-1364
- 41. T. Moon, W. Chu, L. Li, Z. Zheng, Y. Chang (2012) An online learning framework for refining recency search results with user click feedback, Transactions on Information Systems 30(4)
- L. Li, W. Chu, J. Langford, T. Moon, and X. Wang (2012) An unbiased offline evaluation of contextual bandit algorithms with generalized linear models, Journal of Machine Learning Research - Workshop and Conference Proceedings 26 (JMLR W&CP-26)
- 43. P. Bennett, R. W. White, **W. Chu**, S. Dumais, P. Bailey, F. Borisyuk and X. Cui (2012) Modeling and measuring the impact of short and long-term behavior on search personalization, ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR-35) *Test of Time Award*
- 44. W. Chu, M. Zinkevich, L. Li, A. Thomas, and B. Tseng (2011) Unbiased online active learning in data streams, ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD-17)
- 45. L. Zhang, J. Yang, W. Chu, and B. Tseng (2011) A machine-learned proactive moderation system for auction fraud detection, ACM Conference on Information Retrieval and Knowledge Management (CIKM-20 Short Paper)
- 46. L. Li, W. Chu, J. Langford and X. Wang (2011) Unbiased offline evaluation of contextual-bandit-based news article recommendation algorithms, ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM-04) 297-306 Best Paper Award
- 47. W. Chu, L. Li, L. Reyzin, and R. E. Schapire (2011) Contextual bandits with linear payoff functions, International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS-14)
- 48. T. Moon, L. Li, W. Chu, C. Liao, Z. Zheng and Y. Chang (2010) Online learning for recency search ranking using real-time user feedback, International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM-19 Short Paper) 1501-1504

- 49. L. Li, W. Chu, J. Langford and R. E. Schapire (2010) A contextual-bandit approach to personalized news article recommendation, International World Wide Web Conference (WWW-19) 661-670
- 50. S.-T. Park and W. Chu (2009) Pairwise preference regression for cold-start recommendation, ACM Recommender Systems (RecSys-03):21-28
- 51. W. Chu and Z. Ghahramani (2009) Probabilistic models for incomplete multi-dimensional arrays, International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS-12):89-96
- 52. W. Chu and S.-T. Park (2009) Personalized recommendation on dynamic content using predictive bilinear models, International World Wide Web Conference (WWW-18):692-700
- 53. W. Chu, et al. (2009) A case study of behavior-driven conjoint analysis on Yahoo! Front Page Today Module, ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD-15 Industry Track):1097-1104
- 54. R. Silva, **W. Chu** and Z. Ghahramani (2007) Hidden common cause relations in relational learning, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS-20):1345-1352
- 55. K. Yu and W. Chu (2007) Gaussian process models for link analysis and transfer learning, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS-20):1657-1664
- 56. P. K. Shivaswamy, W. Chu and M. Jansche (2007) A support vector approach to censored targets, IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM-07):655-660
- 57. W. Chu and S. S. Keerthi (2007) Support vector ordinal regression, Neural Computation 19(3):792-815
- 58. V. Sindhwani, W. Chu and S. S. Keerthi (2007) Semi-supervised Gaussian process classifiers, International Joint Conferences on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-20):1059-1064
- 59. W. Chu, V. Sindhwani, Z. Ghahramani and S. S. Keerthi (2006) Relational learning with Gaussian processes, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS-19):289-296
- 60. K. Yu, W. Chu, S. Yu, V. Tresp and Z. Xu (2006) Stochastic relational models for discriminative link prediction, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS-19):1553-1560
- 61. S. K. Shevade and W. Chu (2006) Minimum enclosing spheres formulations for support vector ordinal regression, IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM-06):1054-1058
- 62. W. Chu, Z. Ghahramani, R. Krause and D. L. Wild (2006) Identifying protein complexes in high-throughput protein interaction screens using an infinite latent feature model, Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing (PSB-11):231-242
- 63. W. Chu (2006) Model selection: an empirical study on two kernel classifiers, International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN-06):1673-1679
- 64. W. Chu, Z. Ghahramani, A. Podtelezhnikov and D. L. Wild (2006) Bayesian segmental models with multiple sequence alignment profiles for protein secondary structure and contact map prediction, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Computational Biology and Bioinformatics 3(2):98-113
- 65. W. Chu, S. S. Keerthi, C. J. Ong and Z. Ghahramani (2006) Bayesian support vector machines for feature ranking and selection, In I. Guyon, S. Gunn, M. Nikravesh, and L. Zadeh, editors, Feature Extraction, Foundations and Applications Springer:403-418
- 66. W. Chu, Z. Ghahramani, F. Falciani and D. L. Wild (2005) Biomarker discovery with Gaussian processes in microarray gene expression data, Bioinformatics 2005(21):3385-3393
- 67. W. Chu and Z. Ghahramani (2005) Gaussian processes for ordinal regression, Journal of Machine Learning Research 6(Jul):1019-1041
- 68. W. Chu, C. J. Ong and S. S. Keerthi (2005) An improved conjugate gradient scheme to the solution of least squares SVM, IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks 16(2):498-501
- 69. S. S. Keerthi and W. Chu (2005) A matching pursuit approach to sparse Gaussian process regression, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS-18):643-650

- 70. W. Chu and Z. Ghahramani (2005) Preference learning with Gaussian processes, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML-22):137-144
- 71. W. Chu and S. S. Keerthi (2005) New approaches to support vector ordinal regression, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML-22):145-152
- 72. W. Chu and Z. Ghahramani (2005) Extensions of Gaussian processes for ranking: semi-supervised and active learning, Workshop Learning to Rank at (NIPS-18):29-34
- 73. W. Chu, Z. Ghahramani and D. L. Wild (2004) A graphical model for protein secondary structure prediction, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML-21):161-168
- 74. W. Chu, Z. Ghahramani and D. L. Wild (2004) Protein secondary structure prediction using sigmoid belief networks to parameterize segmental semi-Markov models, European Symposium on Artificial Neural Networks (ESANN-05):81-86
- 75. W. Chu, S. S. Keerthi and C. J. Ong (2004) Bayesian support vector regression using a unified loss function, IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks 15(1):29-44
- 76. W. Chu (2003) Bayesian approach to support vector machines, Doctoral Dissertation, National University of Singapore
- 77. K. Duan, S. S. Keerthi, W. Chu, S. K. Shevade and A. N. Poo (2003) Multi-category classification by soft-max combination of binary classifiers, Multiple Classifier Systems (MCS-04) Lecture Notes in Computer Science 2709 Springer:125-134
- 78. W. Chu, S. S. Keerthi and C. J. Ong (2003) Bayesian trigonometric support vector classifier, Neural Computation 15(9):2227-2254
- 79. W. Chu, S. S. Keerthi and C. J. Ong (2002) A general formulation for support vector machines, International Conference on Neural Information Processing (ICONIP-09)
- 80. W. Chu, S. S. Keerthi and C. J. Ong (2002) A new Bayesian design method for support vector classification, International Conference on Neural Information Processing (ICONIP-09)
- 81. S. S. Keerthi, et al. (2002) A machine learning approach for the curation of Biomedical literature KDD Cup 2002 (Task 1), SIGKDD Explorations Newsletter, 4(2) *Honorable Mention*
- 82. W. Chu, S. S. Keerthi and C. J. Ong (2001) A unified loss function in Bayesian framework for support vector regression, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML-18):51-58

References

Available upon request

Date: 2023/01/18